[Music]
You are listening to Golden Rule Radio,
your weekly discussion of the precious
metals markets and the markets closely
associated with the metals. I'm Corey
alongside Miles and Rob, and together we
have over 75 years of experience
advising on and brokering the physical
precious metals. Each week, the three of
us are going to provide you a technical
analysis of the metals charts, but we
also have to cover the underlying
fundamentals and news that helps move
and predict those charts. And if you'd
like to follow along with the images,
you can view this program on YouTube by
going to our website at mlaney.com.
That's mcvany.com.
And without further ado, let's jump into
our weekly recap. Miles,
>> thank you, Tori. I appreciate it. And
we'll take a quick look at the metals
here as everything kind of revolves
around Friday close of the Jackson Hole
meeting as we saw fair bit of volatility
on Friday and then some continuation of
some existing trends expected. So gold
up about 1.75%
and still climbing as we're recording.
Currently sitting at $3,397.
So we're getting real close to that
$3,400 mark. We'll have to see if we
push above it here in the next day or
two. Silver not to be outdone, also up
1.75%,
sitting at $3855
at the moment and also on a little bit
of a weekly rise. The other white
metals, taking a look at platinum.
Platinum slightly up about half a
percent, sitting at around $1342
as it continues after its big push this
past spring. Sit sideways. take a little
bit of a breather in preparation for
what it feels like is coming in the
platinum market. And as I've been
mentioning for the last couple weeks,
platinum sister metal palladium remains
bearish, remains on a declining trend
down 2.5% and is back under $1,100
currently sitting at $1,085.
Also, thanks again to the Friday
announcements following Jackson Hole and
some of the expected interest rate
stuff. We're looking at the S&P up about
1.6%
on the week. That wasn't the whole story
as the S&P put in another slightly
higher high than the previous highs. S&P
all-time highs again this past week
following Friday's news. And finally,
not surprised, dollar down all over the
place this past week, but it is down
very slightly, basically even, sitting
at 98.2, but a lot of volatility over
Friday and Monday as we saw a big
decline and a bounce back in the dollar.
So, boys, where do we want to start this
week? Taking a look at the precious
metals. And I think more importantly,
Tori, don't hold me. I didn't actually
say this out loud, but this may be a
week where the fundamentals matter more
than the charts.
>> Well, the charts are still fun to look
at. I mean, that volatility from Friday
is kind of what we are expecting up or
down. We didn't know what Powell was
going to say from Jackson, Wyoming. Yes,
he came out dovish, which means there's
a real chance that a Fed lending rate
cut. And of course, the markets love
that. But of course, gold's going to
jump because it's going to drive the
dollar lower and it's going to drive all
assets higher. and we'll see what ends
up actually playing out. My concern with
that being such a focus of the
volatility is that we don't know for
sure. I mean, it's already the fact that
we've seen odds go way down that we
would see more than one rate cut if we
do get one in September.
>> Yeah, we talked about this in our prep
for the show. I mean, everybody's
focused on rate cuts. What is it that
we're not seeing?
>> Yeah, what is it that we're not seeing?
Why is it so important? There's
certainly pros and cons and we went into
that in last week's show. All these
arguments for and all these arguments
against,
>> but it's almost like the debate is over.
Like they're set on rate cuts and I
don't understand necessarily why because
inflation is hot. So people are saying
Chairman Powell has caved and that this
is merely political. Well, the only
reason that it's even on the table is
because of the bad jobs numbers. So they
have this dual mandate, the Federal
Reserve, to reduce unemployment and
reduce inflation, keep it in their
target of 2%. They've done a terrible
job of each of those mandates
management, you know, from over the last
number of years.
>> Which do you choose?
>> Yeah,
>> you can't just equally do bad in both.
That of course
>> right now that's kind of the case. I
mean, they've been obviously really
focused on inflation. the labor market,
the unemployment numbers got so
artificially low that they didn't have
to worry about the jobs numbers. They
just could focus on inflation. Well,
little did they know the Bureau of Labor
Statistics was going to come out and
just decimate all of 2024's numbers and
2025. They ended up having just in May
and June, we reduced more than 400,000
jobs. I mean, we're down almost 500,000
jobs in the US payroll data in 2025, and
that's big news. That is what has the
Fed spooked. So, Pal said, quote, "The
shifting balance of risks may warrant
adjusting our policy stance," unquote.
So, that policy stance isn't happening
because inflation is at 2% like the Fed
wants. It's not. It's running. It's
climbing. It's going to top out over 3.3
by December would be my guess. And with
CPI and PPI coming out so strong, why
have the risk shifted? Well, because
it's the deterioration of the labor
market.
>> I'm sitting here thinking to myself,
what else could they cut from the
inflation calculation to keep the
numbers low? Cuz they're kind of running
out of things, right? I think there's
only like seven things left in
calculating price inflation and priced
in gold.com. I don't know if any of our
listeners are familiar with that, but
they do take the time to go back and
calculate inflation rates based on how
the government calculated inflation 30,
40, 50 years ago. So, there is that
little known trick where if you don't
like the numbers, just remove some of
them. And I'm kind of wondering how
quickly they're going to run out of
things to remove. Well, I can eradicate
the entire Bureau of Labor Statistics if
we just use the postage stamp index as
our reflection of inflation.
>> There you go. That's like priced in
gold.
>> Yeah. I mean, it is. I mean, that's the
government running a business. But
that's the real world. That's the post
office. As inefficient as it is, it's
still pretty efficient. And their costs
continue to rise every year.
>> Welcome to life in general. That's been
the case throughout the last 50 years
since we separated from gold and Nixon
closed a gold window. And in fact, the
last time the Federal Reserve cut rates
into rising inflation. So we have rising
inflation again. Yeah.
>> The last time the Federal Reserve cut
rates into rising inflation was in the
1970s. And we all know what happened by
79. Inflation was out of control. It
ends up bringing in new administration
under Reagan. Vulkar as Fed chair. he
has to get super aggressive with raising
rates to cool the inflation. But I'm not
saying that we're going to have like
this incredible 15% plus inflation
again. I'm just saying that you're
pouring fuel on this fire of inflation
if you cut rates in September. And
everybody wants it because it makes
borrowing cheaper and it means business
can operate more efficiently and borrow
more and hire more people and pay better
wages. I get all the economic stimulus
piece, but it comes at a cost
>> and they can't really afford to let
interest rates go up because of the debt
service.
Trump wants to lower the value of the US
dollar. I mean being the reserve
currency of the world is wonderful
because you can print money and buy
everybody else's products but at the
same time you evviscerate your own
manufacturing infrastructure because you
cannot compete in the global arena
because your currency is too strong. So
he's trying to do so many things at
once. We need to at some point dive deep
into the next thing that this
administration is going to spring on us.
>> And we know not only is it weaker
dollar, but it's drive revenue. If
you're not getting it from taxes, you're
driving revenue now through tariffs.
You're driving revenue now through
foreign investment.
>> Well, you're getting foreign investors
diverting from their money that's
already in Treasury debt to keep it here
in the US. They don't want that money to
leave. So they're incentivizing them to
invest in US manufacturing
infrastructure.
>> Sure. This was that thing you talked
about last week, Rob, because I don't
want to get past a point you made a
second ago that I think we're going to
want to circle back to is you said while
everybody's focused on the inflation and
the rate cut discussion, what's
happening on the other side of the table
that nobody's looking at? And I think
that's what you're hinting at, if I'm
not wrong.
>> I am. I mean, we can go back to the
beginning of the year when Secretary
Treasury Scott Vent said within the next
12 months, we're going to monetize the
asset side of the US balance sheet for
the American people. We are going to put
the assets to work. That was 7 months
ago.
>> And that means that the government owns
a whole bunch of stuff. It's either not
looked upon as a productive asset or
it's not valued accurately or correctly.
>> You could listen to Howard Lnik. He's
the Secretary of Commerce and he said,
"We have a $6.5 trillion budget. We have
a $4.5 trillion revenue stream. Our
total GDP is 29 trillion and now our
debt is over 37 trillion." And Ledick
said, "We're going to hell." What is the
balance sheet of the United States of
America? what's everything we own and he
said I think it's 500 trillion
>> so that would just evaporate in terms of
the 37 trillion in debt you just erase
it you hit the reset by monetizing
assets so what are those assets
>> okay when they say this what is their
solution and what their solution is is
the United States sovereign wealth fund
this is a statebacked investment
strategy using a sovereign wealth fund
to hold and unlock national assets on a
statebacked balance sheet. This SWF will
remonetize not just gold, but every
asset tied to the US, land, oil, mineral
rights, everything.
>> Yeah.
>> And here's how it works. Like Anoir oil
field up in Alaska, it's proven to have
more reserves in Saudi Arabia. That all
goes into the sovereign wealth fund and
it turns out a royalty. Just think if
the US government collected a royalty on
that oil forever. Now other countries do
this. Okay.
>> Sure. Saudi Arabia, for example.
>> Yeah. Or golly, uh, China does this.
Norway does this. Russia.
>> Russia. Okay. But there's other idle
resources sitting in the US. There's a
mine called the Pebble Mine in Bristol
Bay, Alaska. It has 80 billion pounds of
copper, 107 million ounces of gold, and
many other important minerals waiting to
be brought into production. But it takes
about 10 years to get all the approval
from all the different agencies and get
it open. So instead of the government
granting mining licenses, the US simply
takes a cut of the profits on US lands
and they cut the permitting process from
10 years to 10 weeks.
>> Well, I think we could certainly benefit
from seeing that. I mean, even if all
that's doing is driving tax revenues
because if the government wasn't taking
this kind of nationalizing
business approach, which is what
concerns me, like this is certainly
government large s and stepping in. I
very much.
>> I get again, we're driving revenues.
We're driving government income in a
sense. It's like you looking for another
way to get some passive income going
while you're working full-time Monday
through Friday as a household. So, the
government's doing that. Great. I doubt
it's going to equate to lower taxes from
an income tax standpoint. They're not
going to let us off the hook, but it
could reduce the debt. I I see the
beauty of that. And yet, it's also
concerning from the standpoint of that's
not free market either. No, it's not.
>> Who's going to get the preferential
treatment?
>> Exactly. This is big government
directing big business and who benefits.
Now, the information I'm pulling this
from is from Goldfix and International
Man, but I know they're telling the
truth because we've got the quotes. We
know what they've been told to do. And
listen, Howard Lnik was the CEO of Caner
Fitzgerald, a major Wall Street insider.
These guys know all about financializing
assets. This is what Wall Street does
when they bring companies public. But
instead of giant wind turbines or solar
panel farm next door, Americans are
going to have to deal with their forests
being harvested, coal mines reopened,
gas wells down the street. You get the
picture.
>> Well, yeah. I mean, they're already
financializing carbon. Yeah.
>> Right. And wind and things that you
can't even see. And so of course this
seems like certainly a creative if not
effective solution for just the bottom
line if you're just talking about the
math.
>> Okay, let's say we give the Trump
administration the benefit of the doubt
that they are doing this for the right
reasons. Well, what about the next guys?
It reminds me a lot of when the Bush
administration put into effect the
Patriot Act. You could assume that they
were doing that well-intentioned, but
then next administrations came along and
used the Patriot Act not against the
people it was intended to, but against
Americans themselves. So, this is all
very concerning. I get it. They can
either print money, default, let a
depression happen, or try to find a way
out. This is their way out. I just don't
like the direction in terms of the
merger of big business and big
government. That really concerns me.
Well, and my big concern, there's been
screaming opposition for decades about
the leverage that varying lobbying
groups and industry has over Washington
already. Who's going to get voting
rights over the sovereign wealth fund,
>> the highest donor? Is it going to work?
I don't know how the system works, but
are we looking at something similar to
common stock voting rights?
>> Rockefeller,
>> you know, are we Yeah, exactly.
Robert's
>> acceptable
poll. That's a good That's a deep pull.
>> It is a deep pull.
>> So, here's where I start getting
frustrated with this is are we just
selling off the United States to the
highest bidder? And I can understand how
the short-term net positive ends up
giving a brief injection to the United
States economy as a whole and possibly
if not probably puts a significant dent
in the overspending and might even lower
overspending in years in the future. But
I know a couple things about the United
States because I've lived here a while
and that's at any point down the road
that we curtail or rearrange how our
spending goes, we immediately find a new
thing to go waste money on to fill the
gap.
>> You're so right on that, Miles. Every
time we raise a tax to solve a problem,
the tax never goes away.
>> They'll put toll roads out on highways
to pay for it, and once it's paid for,
they never take them down.
>> Yeah, toll roads a good example. Well,
I'll tell you the other thing this is
going to do is it's just going to widen
the wealth gap. So, the wealth gap in
the United States has gotten so out of
control. In the 1990s, the wealth gap
between the top 1% and the bottom 50%
was $3 trillion. And now that gap is 40
trillion because.1% of Americans own
almost six times more wealth than the
bottom 50% of Americans. And I know that
sounds like political jargon, but it
really does matter because you end up
concentrating power, influence, and
everything that goes along with that
into a very small number of people. That
was not the way the free market was
designed. I know.
>> So, this is meddling in the free market,
which disadvantages people while
advantaging others.
>> Well, it is supposed to put more and
more people to work. Well, and I get
that. I mean,
>> the bottom 50%. Tori's over here
channeling his inner Bernie Sanders.
>> You know,
>> I mean, I hate to even go down this
road, but it's important because that's
where we're going. I mean, this isn't an
option. Okay, this is a stated fact.
This is where we're going. And people
need to deal with this. And what does
that mean for the US dollar? Because a
lot of this also hinges on a weaker US
dollar policy. Does the sovereign wealth
fund become a pool of assets available
at some point decades down the road to
be tapped for the right necessity?
I don't know. Sort of like social
security was. I'm always hesitant when
we're talking about the government
rolling out a quote unquote voluntary
program.
>> Well, I'll tell you, even if this
doesn't happen, nothing changes because
from an insurance standpoint, it's going
to happen on some scale. Well, it
already is happening such as Intel and
and some of the other things they're
doing with rare earth minerals and all
that. It's been happening in different
market sectors. And then in if you're on
the right side of the fence in that
market sector, i.e. education or
healthcare, you're making a mint.
Whereas those that are not are falling
further behind. So what do you do
listener? I know you're tired of hearing
us say this, but honestly all roads do
lead to gold. And in this instance, all
roads lead to assets. You have to own
assets. You can't be sitting in dollars.
Now, equities can count as assets.
Miles, you showed us the S&P. It's not
just the S&P. The NASDAQ, the the Dow
Jones Industrial. All these equity
markets are at all-time highs. They're
adjusting for a weaker dollar. Gold up
105%. Cryptocurrencies doing what
they're doing. All predicated on the
weakening of the dollar and the loss of
purchasing power. So, you have to own
assets. And if this rate cut comes, the
S&P is going to love it because when the
Fed has cut rates, when the S&P has been
within 2% of its all-time highs, and
Miles, you already pointed out, we're
there already. We're at an all-time high
this week. When the Fed has done that 20
out of the last 20 times, the S&P rose
an average of 13.9% over the following
12 months. Guys, that's economic
stimulation. That's great. But gold's
going to do that.
>> Yeah. even even more in spades, right?
Every asset's going to do that. That's
driving inflation because you're driving
money supply. You're making it easier
through credit
>> and through these digital created items
like cryptocurrencies and otherwise,
you're stimulating the money supply. And
when you do that, everything goes up.
And that's why you better be sitting in
some assets. You better be owning
assets,
>> right? you know, you're going to see the
money multiplier and the velocity of
money picking up. The last thing I want
to say about nationalizing and
financializing
our $500 trillion worth of America, we
have the cleanest air. We have the
cleanest water from any other country
and we're going to sacrifice that. We
just are. And also people sitting in
just bank accounts with assets not doing
anything. The only way to get through
this with all the changes that are
coming is to actually own real assets
that you own and control. And gold is
the premier of all.
>> It is. And gold's telling a story right
now.
>> This program will be on YouTube each
week as well. So you can see the visual
charts and images. And the best place to
go actually for that is our website
which is mlaney.com/news.
That's mcvany.com/news.
I think we need to come back to gold
from a technical analysis standpoint.
>> Yeah, it's about time. We're halfway
through the show already.
>> In fact, we're almost done with the
show. We got to hurry.
>> Well, the miners are telling a story.
It's not just the spot price.
>> Yeah, the miners are telling a story.
And I think it's fascinating. If you
look at the graph of junior miners,
they're doing one thing, but the ratio
between the junior miners and the value
of gold is a very interesting chart.
Miles, pull those up. Sure. Yeah. I was
looking at the miners earlier because
obviously anybody who's sitting in a
minor position, especially the juniors,
just the tear that we've seen some of
the not just gold miners, but you know,
we're in the gold industry, so that's
what we focus on. and we're coming into
a multi-year channel ceiling where we'll
very likely see a little bit of let's
say competition between the bulls and
the bears. I mean, the Bulls have been
pretty much in control of the miners
since about the beginning of 2024. So,
it's been a year and a half now. And I'm
looking at this going, okay, believe it
or not, despite being the office keragin
when it comes to gold, I actually am
arguably short-term bullish on the gold
medal. You know, from a chart
perspective, I like pullbacks and I'm
always rooting for one to happen. But
realistically, as this sideways pause
has taken place over the last couple of
months, the longer this goes on, the
less likely it is gold is going to come
down unless everything does. You know,
the everything bubble pops like 2008. So
unless something like that happens, I'm
bullish on gold. So on the flip side,
I'm looking at the miners and going,
"Yeah, the miners need to take a break."
And the last couple times the miners
have taken a break, we're talking about
significant declines, like 75%
of the rise type of declines. The junior
miners are very volatile. They don't
just take casual corrections. They take
very aggressive corrections. So I then
looked at that and I said, "Okay, well,
what's the correlation between the guys
digging it out of the ground and the
stuff itself?" So just like we do with
other things, I went and looked at the
relative value of gold divided by the
miners and I found kind of the opposite
idea where it is such an inverse
relationship.
>> Great correlation.
>> Yeah. Inverse correlation. Yeah.
>> Yeah. both rising. Obviously, gold is
slowly becoming more valuable compared
to the miners over time as the bottom of
that chart is rising. But as the miners
have been hitting a top, we've been
looking at a bottom of this. And I'm
sitting here thinking to myself, I can't
go out and recommend this to people, but
is it time to pull profits out of the
guy digging it out of the dirt and just
buy the stuff outright for a little bit?
Well, I think you can make that case,
Miles, because everybody chases the
rise. You know, everybody looks at the
price action over here or over there and
they want to jump on the momentum, but
that momentum is probably going to
reverse, whereas the physical gold
itself will continue to rise. I think
now is a great time to take profits out
of your mining position and move it into
physical. If the equities markets have a
major pullback, if we have a crashed,
right, the miners get decimated, the
physical gold does not, in fact, the
spot price can come down a little bit
and the physical market can see premium
increases and it will be a
>> you have this major separation between
the price of a Kruegerand versus the
spot price in New York.
>> Yes. And certainly the mining shares and
what they did historically, they could
be in mutual funds and get pulled down.
So, you do have to be careful to own the
physical asset is what we specialize in.
what we focus on and all of this is
predicated in the short term this next
quarter by the Federal Reserve rate
policy and we will see what happens. My
bet is it's one and done that we'll get
a cut in September. the jobs numbers and
the CPI and PPI that are coming out
right before that are going to
discourage them a little bit and it's
going to be it and we're not going to
see the real estate rally that everybody
was hoping for and we will learn a lot
after that September 17th decision.
>> Yeah. And next week we're going to talk
about the one last thing that this
administration is focused on which
concerns you and your money. Well, a
quarter point rate cut only helps uh
current homeowners in Blackwater. So, I
don't actually know how that's going to
help anybody, but maybe that's just me.
So, that's going to do it this week for
Golden Rule Radio. As always, we
appreciate you stopping by. If you liked
what you heard, we encourage you to head
on over to our website. That's
mulvini.com.
mcvany.com.
You can find us on Twitter at a gold or
Facebook at Melvin Financial. And as
always, if you'd like to talk to one of
us about your personal portfolio, give
us a call. We can be reached at
800-525-9556.
Thanks for listening and have a great
week.